Accident. This word carries a negative connotation with it because you feel fearful about something happening.
Nobody should face any such issues, but according to surveys, there were almost 450k road accidents in India in 2019.
Unfortunately, that led to the death of 150k people.
In such cases, it's very important to have some provision for their family members.
That's why a Personal Accidental Policy is important.
In this video, I'll be telling you about how a Personal Accidental Policy could be useful.
Before that, I'd like to share how an accident is defined in this case.
One definition is a road accident, rail accident, or any such case where a means of transport is involved.
The other one is, for example - if you slip on the stairs, or slip in the bathroom, that's also an accident.
In a Personal Accidental Policy, the nature of accident is not necessarily a road accident, but also includes the second cases.
I'm going to share an example of this in the video of a client who's been with us for a long time had a similar accident and what benefit they received from the Personal Accidental Policy.
Accidents are not always in your control, watch this video to see what I mean.
This video was also a kind of accident. Accidents can happen in any form at any time.
Like I was saying, our client slipped on the road and hurt their leg and had to get surgery done. Because of that, they had to be on bed rest for almost 3 months and because of the Personal Accidental Policy, got a weekly benefit known as Temporary Total Disability Benefit.
Let's hear from him what he has to say about it.
Namaskar, my name is Rakesh Kumar Madan and I live in Model Town, Delhi. I experienced a mishap that I'd like to share about with you.
I was going to the market to get some stuff and I slipped. I had to get an operation done on my foot and the doctor recommended me to be on bed rest for at least 3 months.
I had already gotten a Personal Accidental Policy on Gurleen ji's advice due to which I was able to claim my hospital bills. It also covered the losses that I faced due to not being able to work.
I pray that nobody has to face such a thing, and every family should have a Personal Accidental Policy.
Because they already had a Personal Accidental Policy, they could avail this benefit. This is just one scenario where Personal Accidental benefit can be claimed.
First, we'll look at ten things that are important to know about Personal Accidental Policy, which might be myths, or just things you might not know.
1) Accidents don't just include road accidents. Even if you slip on the stairs, or fall on the road, they'd be considered as accidents.
2) The policy compensates the family in case of both accidental death and disability.
3) The policy offers 100% sum assured in case of death due to an accident. If someone has taken a policy of 50 lakh rupees, and death occurs due to an accident, the family is given 50 lakhs as compensation.
4) Primary purpose of a Personal Accidental Policy is to help the family in case of loss of income.
5) Personal Accident Policy can be renewed for your whole life. You can start the policy till 65 years of age, and the premium from 18 years to 65 years of age is the same.
6) Personal Accidental Policy can't be claimed if death occurs in case of illness.
7) Some accidental policies include accidental hospitalization too. The hospitalization immediately after an accident.
8) In some policies, you can add riders too and customize the plan as much as you want. You can add any riders you can think of, including even ones like adventure sports, which is completely excluded in health insurance policies.
If you add the adventure sports rider, and a mishap happens while you're participating in adventure sports, it'll be covered by the policy, the premium would be higher though.
There is a loan protector rider too, where if you've taken a loan, and accidental disability or death occurs, the amount is paid to the family.
If accidental death occurs, the loan is 100% paid off. In cases of accidental disabilities, there are two types: permanent disability and temporary disability.
In case of permanent disability, it's defined how much will be paid at what level of disability. In case of temporary disability, there is a weekly benefit called as Temporary Total Disability.
For the number of weeks you're on bedrest, you'll get compensated under Temporary Total Disability. This makes the policy more attractive. The first two cases are unlikely, but this is something that could happen to anyone.
I have made individual videos for some Personal Accidental Policies that you can watch to get more in-depth information about specific plans, including cost.
The purpose of making this video was to share with you how important a Personal Accidental Policy is. Now that you know what it covers, it's important to know what it doesn't cover.
If you've opted for the adventure sports rider, then it will be covered, else it won't be.
Self-inflicted injuries are not covered, in cases of Personal Accidental Policy, as well as Health Insurance or Life Insurance.
Accidents that are as a result of war.
If you're involved in defense operations, accidental claims are not covered.
If an accident occurs due to participation in a hazardous activity, it is not covered.
If an accident occurs while you're under the influence of alcohol or drugs, it would not be covered.
It's important to know in which scenario the claim won't be paid, and what the accidental policy covers.
It's a fixed benefit policy, compared to Health Insurance which is indemnity, where you get the amount that you paid to the hospital.
Here, there's a fixed benefit, which is a percentage of your sum assured.
Personal Accidental Policy is not that popular in India and the premium is very low, if you calculate. There are many sum assured options available as well, upto 5 crores.
As an example, if you get a policy of 10 lakhs, the premium would be between 1500 to 2000 rupees an year. This includes temporary total disability rider, accidental hospitalization rider.
Compare this with health insurance, which has a much higher premium than this. Since the premium is same for age 18 to 65, older people can also easily get it.
And a very important thing, your health and lifestyle doesn't impact the policy and premium, even if you're not well, or have a critical illness.
I would suggest that get a health insurance for sure, that is important, and definitely get a Personal Accidental Policy to complement that. Whenever your next renewal comes, you can get a Personal Accidental Policy top-up.
We have already uploaded the reviews of two Personal Accidental Policies on our channel, the links are available in the description.
If you have any questions regarding Personal Accidental Policies, feel free to ask. Our phone number and email id are given in the description, or you can comment your question.
If you found the video useful, please share it, and thank you so much for watching the entire video.
A quick reminder, if you aren't already subscribed to our channel, please subscribe and press the bell button too so that you get the right information at the right time.
I'll see you soon, stay safe, take care and bye.